Amelia Marie Smith

:: ameliamsmith10@gmail.com:: 115 Kleyona Avenue Phoenixville, PA 19460 :: 610.496.8606. ::

Professional Summary

Highly motivated and energetic teaching professional with 7+ years of experience seeks an opportunity to showcase the variety and depth of her knowledge obtained through teaching and educational experiences in order to enhance students' performance and develop the growth mindsets in all learners.

Certifications

Elementary Education K-6, Instructional I (PA and MD)

Special Education Certification PK-8 (PA)

Reading Specialist K-12

Program Specialist: Teaching English as a Second Language PK-12 (PA)

Middle School ELA 6-8 (passed required Praxis examination 2013)

Skills Summary

Technology – Mac, iPad, Pages, Google Drive, Dropbox, Turnitin, Promethean Software, SmartTechnology, Microsoft Office Suite, Study Island, Notability, PowerSchool, First in Math, Reading A to Z, Reading Eggs, RAZkids.com, Skyward

Education Programs – Read Naturally, Wilson Fundations, DIBELS, Reading Workshop, DRA, Fountas and Pinnell, Junior Great Books, LLI, Everyday Mathematics, Book Club, Literature Circles, Words Their Way, Journey's, envisionMath, Math in Focus, Lucy Caulkins Writing Workshop, Daily 5, CAFÉ, FOSS Kits, experience using MLA and APA formatting, PSAT and SAT prep, Benchmarking

Professional Experience

Phoenixville Area School District, Phoenixville PA (August 2016- Present)

1st Grade Teacher

- Planned and implementing lessons across all content domains to meet the various needs of the 22 students in the general education classroom
- Implemented Daily 3 math instruction in order to meet the varying needs of all learners
- Developed and implemented lessons for after school math intervention club for both 1st and 2nd grade students
- Differentiated lessons using Fundations, Daily 5 and CAFÉ strategies to assure that all students are on or above grade level and making adequate yearly growth
- Participated in School-Wide Positive Behavior Support Program and implemented strategies such as class, small group and individualized incentives to encourage positive classroom behaviors

Villa Maria Academy High School, Malvern PA (June 2015 to August 2016) Learning Specialist, ESL Program Coordinator and Teacher, College Board SSD Coordinator

- Developed and implemented curriculum for 9th grade language preparatory class, which was designed to provide students a with a directed, guided study course in support of their coursework in core classes as per recommendations in their IEPs
- Provided direct instruction in specific cognitive study strategies to 9th grade language preparatory classes to lay a foundation for success in the high school years
- Launched English as a Second Language program for over 20 international students from China
- Developed and implemented ESL curriculum for international students who have recently entered the school need to learn English in order to be successful in an increasingly competitive global society

Universal Institute Charter School, Philadelphia, PA (August 2014-June 2015) 2nd Grade Elementary School Teacher

- Responsible for all instructional design and implementation of UICS Grade 2 curriculum over all content domains
- Managed a classroom of 25 students in an urban setting at the highest level of poverty
- Designed lessons to meet the diverse needs of all learners and made the lessons culturally relevant to all students
- Coordinated data in order to track students' progress using Benchmarks, DRA, Fountas and Pinnell
- Participated in Children's Literacy Initiative training and group coaching to incorporate CLI into the classrooms at UICS

- Delivered differentiated language arts instruction utilizing the Balance Literacy approach using the Reader's Workshop Guided reading model and the Writer's Workshop model for writing
- Managed a whole classroom behavior modification plan as a motivator to improve conduct and encourage participation for both individual, small group and whole group behaviors for 25 students
- Advocated for students with emotional, behavioral and education needs to assure their needs were met
- Developed a strong and open communication system with parents to create an educational partnership between home and school
- Coordinated field trips for the entire 2nd grade to enhance concepts, provide culturally enriching experiences and to motivate students to want to learn more
- Co-chair of the K-8 talent show
- Member of the school Celebrations Committee to enhance school culture and spirit

Perkiomen Valley School District, Collegeville, PA (November 2011 to August 2014)

Extended Daily Substitute Teacher, Spanish K-5 (January 2014-June 2014)

• Implemented lessons, in Spanish, provided by the regular classroom teacher

Long Term Substitute Teacher, 2nd grade (August 2012-January 2013)

- Responsible for all instructional design and implementation of PVSD Grade 2 curriculum over all content domains
- Developed lessons with a focus toward the PA common core curricular targets
- Managed a classroom behavior modification plan as a motivator to improve conduct and encourage participation for both individual and whole group behaviors for 21 students
- Delivered differentiated language arts instruction utilizing the Reader's Workshop Guided reading model
- Produced standards-based grade reporting
- Assisted with the formulation of Individual Education Programs

Classroom Teacher, Pre-First Grade Summer Program (Summer 2013)

• Utilized strategies for emergent literacy across a wide range of instructional delivery methods

Elementary Instructional Paraprofessional (November 2011-June 2012, January 2013-August 2014)

- Implemented Junior Great Books program for Tier 1 students and provided additional interventions for at risk readers
- Participated in data meetings and contributed to discussions about leveling decisions
- Served as building substitute for grades K-5 including autistic support, learning support, and special area classes
- Planned and led before school PSSA intervention program using Study Island program (Go-Time!)
- Proctored small group PSSA and 4Sight tests
- Administered DRA tests (Level 1 70), High Frequency Word assessments and Math Benchmark assessments (grades K-1st)

Great Valley School District, Instructional Aide (September 2010 to November 2011)

- Organized and reviewed materials with students for skill reinforcement
- Contributed remedial educational and instructional strategies

Phoenixville Area YMCA Assistant Swim Coach (May 2007 to August 2010)

- Assisted head coach with instructing athletes with the rules, regulation, sequipment and techniques of the sport
- Assessed swimmer's skills during competition and practice, and keeps the head coach informed of the athletic performance of swimmers
- Modeled sports-like behavior and maintained appropriate conduct towards students, officials, and spectators
- Mentored student athletes to help them develop and reach their goals

Student Teaching, 4th Grade

Spring Ford School District

October 2013-August 2014 Royersford, PA

• Reading Specialist Student Teaching, 5th-6th grade

Elwyn School

May 2014-August 2014 Media, PA

Special Education Student Teaching, Autistic Support Early Intervention Preschool Program

Professional Development

- Professional Development Workshops: "Strategies to Help Students Become More Independent", "Formative
 Assessment", "PV Teacher Supervision and PA Educator Effectiveness Model", "What You Need to Know About
 the Common Core, and Developing Common Core Resources", "Wilson Fundations Workshop"
- Completed Perkiomen Valley School District's New Teacher Induction Program
- Completed Universal Companies and Villa Maria Academy High School's New Teacher Induction Program
- American Reading Company's "Educating Black and Latino Boys" presented by Dr. Peter Noguera
- Certified in Project WET

Education

Washington College, Chestertown, MD

Bachelors of Arts in Human Development, Elementary Education Concentration, May 2010 Academic All-American Honors, 2010

Cabrini College, Radnor, PA

Special Education Teaching Certificate PK-8, August 2014

Arcadia University, Glenside, PA

Masters in Reading, with Reading Specialist and ESL Program Specialist Certificates, Spring 2016 Graduated with Distinction Graduate Deans Honors List

Community Service

- Coached Special Olympics Swimmers, 2006-2010
- Introduced the Adopt-A-Bear Christmas gift program to the Swim and Crew Teams
- Coordinated the Chestertown "Sneaker Creeper Run" for Ages 0-12 to promote Lung Cancer Awareness
- Developed Swim Quest, a swim meet for physically disabled children and adults
- Volunteered as a moderator/scorekeeper for Montgomery County Reading Olympics

Awards & Recognitions

Washington College, Chestertown, MD

- Dean's List
- Varsity Swim Team Captain
- Academic All-American in Swimming
- Varsity Crew Team Spirit Award 2009/2010
- Competed in NCAA D3 Rowing Championships 2008/2009
- All MARC Varsity Team
- Varsity Crew and Swim Team Member 2006-2010